Marko Kolarek

Berlin, Berlin, Germany



marko.kolarek@protonmail.com



linkedin.com/in/mkolarek

Summary

As a proficient software and data engineer, I build end-to-end data and ML-driven applications in the cloud, primarily on Amazon Web Services and Microsoft Azure.

I provide my clients with thorough planning and consulting expertise combined with efficient project implementation throughout the entire data analytics stack, including data integration, modelling, and team development.

Additionally, I specialize in designing and implementing data architecture and infrastructure, specifically data platforms. Targeting primarily medium-sized enterprises, I provide extensive services, ensuring end-to-end solutions from a single source.

Experience



Data Engineer | Data Architect | Consultant

Freelance

Apr 2024 - Present (1 month)

Staff Data Engineer

GROPYUS

Mar 2023 - Mar 2024 (1 year 1 month)

- Overarching role in data department, participating in daily business of both data teams
- Designing and implementing data architecture, ensuring successful integration with overall IT architecture
- As interim Head of Data, collaborating with product management on product roadmap, aligning with other IT departments and providing higher-level management to data department
- Participated in broad IT infrastructure efforts with planning and implementation, such as service mesh migration

WM Head Of Data

Visual Asset Management (VAAAM)

Apr 2022 - Feb 2023 (11 months)

- Designing and implementing data architecture, ensuring successful integration with the overall IT architecture
- Managing data science, analytics and engineering efforts operationally and professionally
- Working with CTO on data and product strategy, investor and vendor relationships
- Working with CTO to establish VAAAM AG externally as a leader in engineering topics



Nov 2020 - Mar 2022 (1 year 5 months)

- Developed event-based streaming pipelines based on serverless solutions
- Implemented infrastructure for digital twin and related products
- Participated in interviewing, onboarding and mentoring of new and existing colleagues

Senior Data Engineering Consultant

DAIN Studios

Mar 2019 - Oct 2020 (1 year 8 months)

- Developed and maintained existing data ingestion, cleaning and processing pipeline for large remote learning provider
- Designed and implemented data platform for large telecom provider
- Collaborated on various data architecture project proposals

BE2 Cohort Member

Entrepreneur First

Oct 2018 - Jan 2019 (4 months)

- Researched and prototyped different start up ideas, with a focus on deep tech

r⊷ Data Engineer

Flix

Feb 2018 - Sep 2018 (8 months)

- Implemented and maintained data ingestion, cleaning and processing pipelines
- Productionized prototype of machine learning API and deployed it to production

Research Engineer

Zalando

Jul 2016 - Jan 2018 (1 year 7 months)

- Performed A/B test analyses for diverse business and technical features
- Researched advanced statistical analysis methods for automating hypothesis tests
- Implemented and maintained various data ingestion, cleaning and processing pipelines for A/B test analysis automation
- Published and contributed to open-source statistical analysis library ExpAn

Backend Engineer

Zalando

Sep 2015 - Jun 2016 (10 months)

- Implemented system, application and business level monitoring of the A/B testing platform
- Implemented various data ingestion and processing pipelines for A/B test analysis automation

Research Associate

Visage Technologies

Jul 2014 - Jun 2015 (1 year)

- Researched and prototyped various machine-learning based approaches to eye gaze detection

- Implemented eye gaze detection feature of the Visage SDK

Software Engineer Intern

divIT systems

Jul 2013 - Aug 2013 (2 months)

- Implemented a module for the mash.me interactive motion-capture project (face and facial features detection)
- Implemented a QR code reader with basic augmented reality features for a client event

Education



MSc in Information and Communication Technology, Information Processing 2012 - 2014



BSc in Electrical Engineering and Information Technology, Information Processing and Multimedia Systems

2008 - 2012

Licenses & Certifications



C2 Proficiency - Cambridge University Press & Assessment English



Skills

Knowledge Graphs • Cloud Infrastructure • Cloud • DevOps • Data Engineering • Software Architecture • Python (Programming Language) • Data Science • Data Streaming • Terraform